我提议继续坚持
And I say we continue to insist.
教会特权不受世俗的干扰
Upon the church's immunity from secular interference;
而且我们会坚持下去
And we shall continue to insist upon it.
因为这一豁免权
Because that immunity.
是我主授予的
Was ordained by god.
并且这一教会特权
And this immunity from secular interference should extend.
也应由教会的神父和教工享有
To the ordained priests and servants of our holy church.
他们应该免受谋杀等伤害的威胁
And they should be free from the threat.
无论是下毒
Of murder and harm, by the use of poison…
还是其他恶毒的方式 这些信徒唯一的「罪孽」
or any other foul means, when their only crime.
无非是遵从了上帝的旨意
Has been to obey god's law.
维护了教会的圣洁
And uphold the sanctity of the church.
我恳请大家理解…
I beg you to understand…
国王肯定不会允许这种事情的
the king can't allow this.
投票至关重要
The vote is crucial.
无论如何 他都会粉碎教会
One way or another, he must break the church,
从现在 到永远
Now and for always.
- 你好 马克 - 这到底是怎么了 怀特先生
- hey, mark. - what is this, mr. wyatt?
这可是圣诞节 温馨的节日
It's christmas! the season of goodwill.
大家都怎么了？
What's wrong with everyone?
今年一切都不同往日
There's no mirth this year.
- 所以没什么气氛 - 为什么？
- because everything is different. - how?
不知道你注意到没有
in case you hadn't noticed,
王后和她的婢女都不在
the queen and her ladies aren't here.
所以我们就该不开心？
why should we all be sad about that?
正如法国人所说 没有王后的后宫
You know the Franch say A court without ladies.
就像花园没有了鲜花
Is like a garden without flowers.
安妮夫人 您的圣诞礼物
Lady anne, a christmas present.
来自国王陛下
From his majesty.
感谢陛下
thank you, your majesty.
我还为你订制了一张很舒服的床
I've also had a great bed made for you.
就要做好了
It's almost ready.
陛下 来自安妮夫人的礼物
Your majesty, a present from the lady anne.
猎矛
Boar spears.
很显然 是比斯开（西班牙地名）风格的
made after the biscayan fashion, apparently.
这是最上乘的
the best.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Thank you, sweetheart.
还有一件礼物 陛下
another present for your majesty.
拿近点
come closer.
很精致
It's very fine.
- 谁送的？- 王后陛下
- Who sent it to me? - her majesty.
凯瑟琳王后 国王陛下
Queen katherine, your majesty.
我不接受 拿走
I will not receive it. take it away!
别让她扫了雅兴
don't let her spoil everything.
陛下 首相托马斯·莫尔爵士觐见
your majesty, the chancellor sir thomas more.
托马斯爵士
sir thomas.
陛下 安妮女士
majesty. mistress anne.
我带来一份很合时宜的礼物
I have a seasonal gift for you.
请恩准
With your permission.
它提醒我们这个节日的意义
It reminds us of what we have to celebrate.
谢谢你 托马斯爵士 我会珍惜的
thank you, sir thomas. I will treasure this.
我们要尽早会面 托马斯
We must meet soon, thomas.
我们还有很多国事要商讨
There's a great deal to do with the business of management of this kingdom.
关于教会滥用特权的事情
There's still a great clamour against the privileges.
还有很多争论
Enjoyed by the clergy, and their abuse of it.
必定还要采取进一步措施
Further measures will certainly have to be taken.
期待与您探讨 陛下
I look forward to consulting with your majesty.
托马斯
Thomas.
圣诞快乐
Happy christmas.
- 陛下 - 查尔斯
- your majesty. - charles!
- 陛下 - 圣诞快乐
- majesty. - happy christmas.
圣诞快乐
Happy christmas.
- 打网球吗？- 好主意
- game of tennis? - good idea.
- 有件事不知该不该说 - 说吧
- May I speak with you honestly? - I hope so.
你是不是一定要娶波林女士 不计后果
Are you really gonna marry mistress boleyn? whatever the consequences.
不计前嫌？
Whatever her history?
查尔斯 你问这个什么意思
why do you ask, charles?
不计前嫌是什么意思
what do you mean "whatever her history?"
我有确信的消息她和托马斯·怀特曾经有私情
I have it on very good authority that she and thomas wyatt were once lovers.
显然她与托马斯经常私通
Apparently she fornicated with him on many occasions,
有时夜里偷偷溜到他的房间
Sometimes brazenly entering his chambers at night.
我听说过 她否认了
I've heard those rumours. she denies it.
嗯 她当然会否认了 不是吗
well, she would, wouldn't she?
我说了 她说没有
I said she denies it!
圣诞快乐
Happy christmas.
你觉得国王怎么样 克朗默先生？
how do you find the king, mr. cranmer?
我向您起誓 克伦威尔先生
I swear to you, mr. cromwell,
他真的是最善良的王公
that he really is the kindest of princes.
我觉得你遇到了一个大好的机遇
I think you were born at a happy hour.
因为目前看来 你的言行
For it seems, do or say what you will,
国王陛下都会支持的
His majesty will always take it at your hand.
我不这么认为
I am not so conceited.
事实上我只是陛下的一个勤恳的仆人
As to suppose I am anything more to his majesty than a diligent servant.
谦虚为你赢得荣誉
your modesty does you honour.
可是国王陛下很明显认为
But his majesty clearly thinks.
你一定可以胜任更高的职责
that you are destined for better things.
因此他任命你为
Which is why he has appointed you.
派驻神圣罗马帝国的特使
His special envoy to the court of the emperor.
他不可能这样做
he can't possibly do that!
我的意思是… 是说… 为什么选我呢
What… what I mean is… is, why me?
我是个无名小卒 克伦威尔先生
I… I am nothing, mr. cromwell.
陛下非常信任你
his majesty trusts you absolutely.
他知道你比任何人都了解他要事
He knows that you understand his great matter.
作为陛下的代言人
Better than anyone else, and that you take his part.
你最好尽力在皇宫代表他的意愿
You'd better place the most to represent him at the imperial court.
我相信你会非常成功的
I'm sure that you'll be a great success.
你去皇宫的路上 可去纽伦堡转转
And on your way there, you'll have a chance to visit the city of nornberg.
是首个完全由路德教派和改良派管理的城市
The first city wholly run by lutherans and reformers.
一座既没有狂热迷信和盲目崇拜的信徒
A city free of ancient superstitions and idolatry.
也没有罗马教会和滥用特权的牧师的城市
Free of popery and the abuses of the clergy.
我很期待读读你的记述
I shall look forward to your report.
沙福克伯爵也来跟我提了
The duke of suffolk has taken it upon himself to repeat the gossip.
那些关于你和怀特先生的谣言
About you and mr. wyatt.
你相信了？
and do you believe any of it to be true?
如果我相信了
if I did,
我就不会在这跟你散步了
Would I be walking here with you?
我猜
I suppose.
你应该已经把他驱逐出宫了
You've banished the duke from court?
我召唤了法国大使来见我
I've asked the french ambassador to come and see me.
我要他重新起草一份与法国的盟约
I want him to draw up a new treaty of alliance with france.
以转移教皇的威胁
To nullify the threat against the emperor.
挺好的 你知道我对法国情有独钟
I'm glad. you know my sentiments towards france.
可是 冒昧的问…
But, forgive me…
这跟我有什么关系？
What has that got to do with me?
我想见他还有另外一个原因
there is another reason why I want to see him.
我想安排我们一起访问法国
I intend to arrange a visit to france for both of us.
我想正式向法国国王弗兰西斯
I want to present you, formally,
介绍你
To king francis,
作为我未来的妻子
But as my future wife.
及未来的英格兰王后
And the future queen of england.
噢 上帝
oh, my god!
大人 跟你说句话？
your grace. may we speak?
作为坎特伯雷大主教
I am here to inform your grace,
我来这里是告知您
As archbishop of canterbury,
国王打算在国会下一次议会之前
That the king intends to put a bill.
提出一个新的议案
Before the new session of parliament.
关于什么 克伦威尔先生？
what does it concern, mr. cromwell?
首先
in the first place,
议案旨在否认罗马教皇
it means to deny the pope.
以及教皇从收取从英国教会征收的赋税
much of the revenue he now receives from the english church.
同时提案反对我国重要
It also means to lay indictments.
- 神职人员的特权 - 克伦威尔先生
- Against the privileges of leading clergy in this country. - Mr. Cromwell,
这针对神圣教堂的进一步攻击原因何在？
What could be the cause of this further attack upon our holy church?
人们会亲眼看见修道士们
People can see for themselves that the monasteries.
已经坐拥大笔财富
Are already sitting on a great wealth,
这些财富本应用在别处
which could be better applied elsewhere.
本应给那些普通善良的劳动者
For the good of the whole commonwealth. for the good of ordinary,
带来福利
hard-working people.
这对滥用权力的抨击
This does not strike me.
对我来说并不可怕
As an attack against abuses.
但这公开的攻击更是针对
But rather, an open attack.
我们的信仰
Upon our faith…
我们对祖先的信仰 …
and the faith of our ancestors.
大人可以这样判断 可我并不这样想
If that is your judgement, your grace, it is not mine.
国王也不会
Neither is it the king's.
南
Nan!
- 有事吗 夫人？- 替我准备洗澡水
- Yes, madam? - Draw me a bath.
- 散步让我有些冷了 - 好的 夫人
- The walk has made me cold. - Yes, madam.
我有个好消息
I've got such exciting news.
我们要去巴黎了
We're going to paris.
我们将被引见给国王 南
I'm going to be presented before the King.
南
Nan!
今天谁来了？
Who has been in the apartment today?
没人来过 夫人 我并不知情 怎么了？
Nobody, Madam. Not to my knowledge. Why?
这儿有个预言牌阵
Here is a book of prophecy.
这是国王
This is the king,
这是王后…
This is the queen…
这是我
And this is myself,
头被砍下
With my head cut off.
沙福克公爵大人
His grace the Duke of Suffolk.
大人 我已经得到陛下的谕令
Your grace. I have his majesty's order.
把你逐出宫廷
To banish you from court.
你好像冒犯龙颜了
You have displeased him, it seems.
你究竟是何方神圣 克伦威尔先生？
Who are you, Mr. Cromwell?
我觉得我应该认识你 可事实并非如此
I feel like I should know, but somehow I don't.
就如同你所了解到的
I am exactly as your grace finds me.
我尽全力侍奉陛下
I serve his majesty to the best of my ability.
有人告诉我你曾经是个雇佣兵
Some one told me that you were once a mercenary soldier.
我年轻时是做了些事
I saw some action in my youth.
就像大人一样 我确信
As did your grace, I believe.
但我不是逢迎的军人
But I was never a soldier of fortune.
如果冒犯国王 也是出于忠心
If I displeased the king, it was in a good cause.
我相信
I'm sure.
- 虽然有些人会有异议 - 比如你？
- Although some would argue otherwise. - Like you?
我不敢与你争执 大人
I would never have the temerity to argue With your grace.
只是不当着我的面罢了
Not to my face anyway.
这是陛下的命令 你必须立刻离宫
Here is the order. You are to leave court at once.
现在我拿着的
I have here, in my hands,
是在授职仪式上所有神职人员
The oath which all members of the clergy swear to the pope.
对教皇的誓言
At the time of their consecration!
和他们对我们誓言
It is in clean contrast.
绝然不同
To the oath they swear to us.
我亲爱的臣子们…
My beloved subjects…
我们原以为神职人员
We thought the clergy.
是完全服从于我们的臣子
Were wholly our subjects.
但现在我们明白他们半心半意
But now we can see they are only half our subjects…
如果他们还是我的臣民的话 诸位大人
If they are our subjects at all!
诸位大人
My lords,
我要知道你们到底听命于谁？教皇
I demand to know whose subjects are you, the pope's.
还是我？
Or mine?
- 乔治·索科莫图爵士光临 - 乔治·索科莫图爵士
- Sir George Throckmorton, your honour. - Sir george!
很高兴见到你
Very glad to see you.
我知道你是位虔诚的天主教徒
I know you are a good catholic man.
从不怕凭良心说话
Who has never been afraid to speak his conscience.
那么说真的 所有人都该如此吗 阁下
So, in truth, should every man, your honour.
当然 但这阵子 似乎有有许多人
Indeed. But these days, it seems there are many.
被打压的不敢说话 更糟的是
Who can be bullied into silence, or worse,
竟然违背他们的良心做事
to acting against their conscience.
记住我的话 乔治 接下来的几天
Mark my words, George, these next few days.
将决定我们信仰的未来命运
Will determine the future of our faith.
无论克伦威尔先生说什么
Whatever Mr. Cromwell says,
无论他怎么矫饰他的言辞
However he dresses his argument up with honeyed words,
结果都是一样的 他决心
The effects remains the same.He is demanding.
要让所有神职人员都服从国王的意愿
That the clergy submit themselves totally to the king's will and to.
和世俗的权威
secular authority.
愿上帝阻止他不让他成功
God forbid he should ever succeed!
如果他成功了 就不会有教堂 不会有宗教
If he does, there will be no more church, no more religion,
这王国将不再有精神生活
No more spiritual life in this kingdom!
克伦威尔或许还会玷污圣母
Cromwell might as well rape the blessed virgin himself!
阁下
Your honour!
因此我请求你 请求像你一样的人
That's why I'm asking you, asking you and people like you,
保持力量 坚守真理 如果你们这样做
To remain strong and true. If you do,
将会得到上帝巨大的回报
Then you will deserve god's great reward,
你自己也会获得更多的敬拜
And much worship will come to you personally.
相信我
Believe me,
到那时甚至连国王都会感谢你
In time even the king himself will thank you.
我们要感谢
We give thanks.
吾王圣权的恩惠
For the reign of the king's grace,
我们请求上帝保佑吾王
And we ask god's blessing on him.
和他的臣民…
And on his people…
但在这个神圣的日子 我们有必要说
But on this holy day, we are obliged to say.
殿下的有些传教士
That some of your highness's preachers are these days.
就像我们在亚哈王统治时「
Too much like those of Ahab's days,
所看到的那些信口雌黄
In whose mouths was found.
有着虚伪和狡诈的灵魂
A false and lying spirit.
那些传教士拥有的 是虚假的福音
Theirs is the gospel of untruth,
他们甚至推崇国王的特权和自由
Not afraid to tell of licence and liberty for monarchs,
这些是任何一个信奉主的国王
Which no christian king should dare.
从不敢冒犯的
Even to contemplate!
我恳请殿下留心
I beseech your highness to take heed,
别再走你们所在的路
Not to pursue the path you seem to be taking,
不然你们一定会成为下一个
Or you will surely follow Ahab,
迎娶了青楼婊子的亚哈王
Who married the whore jezebel,
你们的下场也会和他一样
And surely will incur his unhappy end, that dogs.
狗会像舔尽亚哈王的血一样舔食你们那
Will lick your blood as they licked Ahab's…
为上帝所避讳和禁锢的血液
Which God avert and forbid!
放手 你们这些走狗
Unhand me, you dogs!
我是上帝的使徒 放开我
I am a man of God! Unhand me!
放开我
Unhand me!
我是上帝的使徒 放开我
I am a man of God! Unhand me!
你这无耻的托钵僧 如果不马上闭嘴
You shameless friar! You'll be sewn in a sack.
你会被缝进袋子 然后被丢进泰晤士河
And thrown into the thames if you don't speedily hold your tongue.
省省吧 这只能吓吓你的走狗
Keep your threats for your fellow courtiers.
我们托钵僧不会在意你的那些话
As for us friars, we take no account of them at all,
因为我们知道 如同存在于大地一样
Since we know very well that the way to heaven is as good.
天堂之路也在水中
by water as by land.
国王驾到 全体起立
All rise for the king!
国会开始
Parliament is in session!
诸位大人
My lords…
诸位阁下
Your graces…
你们决定了吗？
Have you come to a decision?
是依然反对我
Do you still deny me,
还是服从
Or do you accept.
你们国王的权威？
The authority of your king?
大人
Your grace.
陛下 这是…
Your majesty. here is…
神职人员…
The submission of the clergy…
对陛下的绝对服从
To your majesty's will.
- 谢谢你 大主教 - 他们已经投降了
- Thank you, archbishop. - They've surrendered.
教会已经被瓦解
The church is broken.
我从没想过在我有生之年
I never thought I would live.
能看到英格兰的这一天
To see this day in england.
现在 国会的行动给予了异教徒
Now, by act of parliament, heretics are free.
在伦敦不受检查 自由来往的权利
To swan around the streets of london without check.
如果可以哭泣 托马斯爵士
If I could weep, Sir Thomas,
我将流出血泪
I would weep tears of blood.
托马斯·莫尔爵士觐见
Sir Thomas More.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
陛下
Your Majesty.
我来是要辞去首相的职务
I come to offer my resignation from my post as chancellor.
我请求您能准许我
I ask your highness to allow me.
从公众生活中抽身
To withdraw from public life,
让我能有更多的时间
So that I may spend what time remains to me.
充实我的灵魂
Provisioning my soul,
尽职与上帝
And in the service of god.
这袋里装着代表我职权的印章
In this bag I carry the great seal of my office,
现在我已无力拿起它
Which I find now too heavy to hold.
我十分欣慰的…
I discharge you…
解除你的职务
Most willingly.
托马斯爵士 在你为我供职期间
In everything you have done for me, sir thomas,
你一直…
You have always…
尽职 高尚
Been good and gracious,
不管是在私人生活
Both in private.
- 还是在公共事务中 - 陛下
- And in public affairs. - Majesty.
我以我的荣誉担保
I promise on my honour.
我决不会在公共场合
That I will never speak publicly.
提及陛下的要事
Of your majesty's great matter.
但是现在 以私人的名义
But now, in private,
作为一个曾受陛下信任的朋友
I must confess to you, as someone.
我必须要承认
Who once enjoyed your majesty's confidence and friendship,
我深深地相信
My deepest belief that, if your majesty saw fit.
如果陛下能与凯瑟琳王后和解
To be reconciled with queen katherine,
那您王国所经历的分裂和遭受的创伤
The divisions and hurts of your kingdom.
将马上得到治愈
Would at once be healed.
这就是我想说的
There. I've said it.
从此我将不再开口
And now my lips are forever sealed.
托马斯
thomas!
我要你坚守对我的承诺
I will hold you to that promise.
莫尔宫
The More.
伊丽莎白女士 我受陛下之命前来
lady elizabeth. I come on the king's business.
怀特先生
mr. wyatt.
凯瑟琳夫人在哪里
where is the lady katherine?
陛下在做祷告 将要有一段时间
her majesty is at prayer and will be for a long time.
我们不能打扰她
She cannot be disturbed.
- 我受命前来送这个 - 这是什么
- I am charged to deliver this. - what is it?
收回凯瑟琳女士王室珠宝的谕令
a command that lady katherine return her official jewels.
伊丽莎白女士…
Lady elizabeth…
- 你想要什么 - 你知道我想要什么
- what do you want? - you know what I want.
怀特先生 我从没兴趣成为你的情人
mr. wyatt, i have no intention of becoming your mistress.
也不想成为任何人的情人
Nor anyone else's, for that matter.
我在结婚时必须是个处女 但我怀疑
I shall be a virgin when I marry, but I doubt.
自己是不是会结婚
I shall marry at all.
也许做个虔诚的信徒更好
I would rather be a bride of christ.
修女？我可不那么认为
a nun? I don't think so.
看看你的口袋
Check your pocket.
「上帝您是否知晓我内心深处的渴望…
"would god thou knewest the depth of my desire…
「我是否能够期望 即使我根本不配…
"then might I hope, thou nought I can deserve…
拥有一些平息我炙热的欲望之火的恩泽「
Some drops of grace would quench my scorching fire."
我相信我法国之旅的所有事宜
I trust all the arrangements.
- 都已经安排好了吧？- 是的
- Have been made for my visit to france? - yes, everything is prepared.
都准备好了陛下 弗兰西斯国王
And ready, your majesty.
十分期待与您的再次会面
king francis Is most eager to see your majesty again,
以及共同签订一份友好联盟协议
And to sign with you a new alliance of friendship.
安妮女士怎么样呢？
and the lady anne?
她将会受到最高的待遇
she will be received with all due honour.
我很高兴你这么说
I'm very glad to hear it.
我只想把最好的给她
I only want the best for her.
我希望这是一次特别之旅
I want this visit to be special.
不希望有任何人来破坏
And I don't want anything to spoil it.
明白吗？
Do you understand me?
是的 完全明白
I understand. completely.
法兰西国王也明白
And so does his majesty.
谢谢 斯米顿先生
thank you, mr. smeaton.
亲爱的
sweetheart.
陛下这就是我和您提过的年青绅士
Your majesty this is the young gentlemen I told you about.
- 马克·斯米顿 - 斯米顿先生
- Mark smeaton. - mr. smeaton.
安妮女士和我提过很多你的事
The lady anne has told me a lot about you.
她说你很会演奏音乐
She says you play very well.
为我们演奏些什么吧
Play something for us.
遵旨 陛下
your majesty.
我知道沙福克公爵口不择言是个错误
I know it was wrong for the duke of suffolk to say what he did,
但你觉得我们是否可以饶恕他？
But do you think it's possible we could forgive him?
如果你这么快就饶恕了他
if you forgave him so quickly,
有些人会认为他说的是真的
Some people might think that there was some truth To what he said.
不错 但为了驳倒他们
yes, but to refute them,
为了能正面的回答这个问题
To answer the matter directly.
证明我有多信任你
and to show how much I trust you,
我有更大的举动
I will do a more important thing.
我会邀请怀特先生与我们同去法兰西
I will invite mr. wyatt to come to france with us.
这样就没人会说我嫉妒
That way, no one can accuse me of jealousy,
他们一点也不会怀疑
Or the slightest suspicion.
亲爱的 他们没有理由怀疑你
my love, you have no reason to be suspicious.
以后也不会
Nor will ever have.
我从我们的朋友克朗默那里
I've received a most illuminating letter.
收到一份非常有启发的信
from our friend cranmer.
好像在纽伦堡
It appears that, in nuremberg,
神职人员是允许结婚的
Clergy are allowed to marry.
克朗默先生充分利用了这点
And mr. cranmer has taken full advantage of that fact.
- 你说他结婚了？- 看上去是
- you mean he got married? - so it seems.
这对他的事业没什么好处
well, it won't do his career much good here.
非法结婚
Being illegal.
不错 神职人员结婚现在是违法的
well, it's illegal for the clergy to marry now, yes.
你这是什么意思？
what are you saying?
你想让牧师可以结婚？
You want priests to be able to marry?
也许我还没向你解释清楚 勋爵大人
perhaps I have never fully explained myself to you, your lordship.
当我对你们攻击时
When, to you and to others, I have attacked the practices.
你们的天主教堂活动
Of the catholic church.
朝拜 对圣人的崇拜
Pilgrimages and the worshipping of saints,
向十字架匍匐顶礼
Crawling to the cross,
对牧师的尊敬
Veneration of priests…
我从没有兴趣对他们进行改革
I've never been interested in reforming them. no.
我真正的 唯一的兴趣
My real, my only interest.
在于毁灭他们
Is in destroying them.
正好相反 秘书官现象
On the contrary, mr. secretary.
我认为我们都很非常了解对方
I think we understand each other perfectly.
还有一些事
there is something else,
一件非常重要的事
Something very important, which must be done.
必须再去法兰西之前解决
Before we can sail for france.
什么事？
what?
告诉我
Tell me!
让路 为安妮女士让路
Make way for the lady anne. make way.
昭告天下所有人等 贵族们 先生们
To all and singular, as well nobles and gentiles as others.
以及出席的各位大人们 我王龙颜大悦
To whom these presents shall come, it is the king's pleasure,
钦此爵位封授状
by this patent,
授予安妮·波林女士
To confer on the lady anne boleyn,
其本人及其子嗣后裔
In her own right, and on her offspring,
世袭彭布罗克女侯爵的贵族头衔
The noble title of marquess of pembroke.
据此封授状 另赐领地
And also by this patent, to grant her lands.
年收入10万英镑
Worth 100, 000 pounds a year,
以维护她的尊贵
For the maintaining of her dignity.
你的爵位封授状
the patent of your nobility.
谢谢陛下
thank you, your majesty.
国王陛下
His majesty the king.
以及彭布罗克女侯爵安妮·波林女士
And the lady anne boleyn, Marquess of pembroke.
主耶稣基督
Corpus domini nostri jesu christi.
愿您的圣体保佑获得永生
Custodiat tu in vitam aeternam.
我们深爱的渥兰大教主
Our dearly beloved archbishop warham.
他已平静地离去
he died peacefully…
如果要在此刻说些什么
If one can say such a thing at such a time.
他也许 幸运地正在通往天堂之路
he is, perhaps, fortunate to be gathered now into heaven,
在他深爱的
Before the final ruin.
并一直服务的教会被毁之前
Of the church he loved and served.
你辞职了 托马斯爵士 因为这场灾难？
you are resigned then, sir thomas, to our ruin?
我不知道还能做些什么
I don't know what else can be done.
我们挺身迎战却失败而归
We fought, and we failed.
我现在只想平静地离开这是非之地
All I want now is to be left in peace.
进行我的写作和祷告
To write and pray.
当然我们仍有责任为了天主教的利益而战
surely we have a duty still to act in the interests of christendom,
无论要付出什么代价
Whatever the cost!
我并不惧怕代价
I have no fear of the cost.
只是我已经
But I have…
发誓远离尘世
Abjured the public realm.
它不再吸引我了
It no longer interests me.
就像它再也不会吸引主教大人了
As it no longer interests his grace.
达瑞尔夫人
mistress darrell.
我来还你的诗
I came to give you your poem back.
你不能把诗退回来 就像不能退一个吻
you cannot give a poem back. or a kiss.
或者一个想法
Or a thought.
你不开心我很难过
I'm sorry that you are unhappy.
像被燃烧着 如你所说
Burning, as you say.
- 但这和我没有一点关系 - 没关系？
- I'm sure I've done nothing to cause it. - nothing?
我的小姐 你正是这一切之因
My lady, you are full of causes.
你的头发…
Your hair…
你的眼睛…
Your eyes…
你的双唇…
Your lips…
所有这些都是我渴望之源
All are causes of my desire.
我必须要回去做事了
I must go to mass.
我知道 我知道
I know you must. I know.
就再待一会
Stay a moment.
你在干什么？
Oh, what are you doing?
给你一个机会
Giving you a chance.
来赎罪
To be penitent…
我美丽的 虔诚的女士
My beautiful, pious lady.
玛格丽特
margaret,
亲爱的女儿
Darling daughter…
我可能将要
It might come to pass.
为我的信仰付出代价
That I could be held to account for my beliefs.
但是国王同意你为你的良知说话
but the king allows for your conscience…
不管如何我们还是有所准备的好
nonetheless, it's better to be prepared.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我的宝贝
sweetheart…
我们必须讨论我殉道的可能性
We must discuss the question of martyrdom.
不 不
No, no.
听我说
listen.
因为我觉得如果我的妻儿
Because if I thought my wife and children.
能鼓励我为了正义的事业而牺牲
Would encourage me to die in a good cause,
我会感到很欣慰
It would so comfort me,
由于这种快乐
That in great joy I would.
我会含笑九泉
Merrily run to death.
求你了
please.
Please.
父亲
oh, father!
你觉得怎么样
what do you think?
这些服饰都是法国流行的款式
They are all in the french fashion.
这是您赐给我的锦缎
This is the damask you gave me.
你喜欢吗
Do you like them?
- 我要你为我骄傲 - 我会的
- I so want you to be proud of me! - oh, i will be.
这些会为你增光添彩
And these will help.
英格兰王后佩戴的珠宝
These are the jewels of the queens of england.
我重新为你准备的
I shall have them reset for you.
我的心情难以言表
I don't know what to say.
你当然知道如何表达
yes, you do.
我爱你
I love you.
时时刻刻恋着你
I love you with my every breath.
深爱着你
With every fibre of my being.
我爱你 我属于你
I love you and I am yours.
- 我也属于你 - 等等
- and I am yours. - wait!
你一直对我关爱有加
You have been so kind to me…
亲爱的 让我来服侍你
Let me be kind to you. my love…
我亲爱的…
My love…
- 你要与国王一同前往法国？- 是的
- you are travelling with the king to france? - I am.
你是否考虑在抵达之后执行任务
will you consider carrying out your mission while you are there?
是的 机会千载难逢
that's a good opportunity. yes.
如果你成功暗杀国王的妓女
If you succeed in killing the king's whore,
你将受到上帝的恩泽
You will be the beloved of god,
得到教皇和神圣罗马皇帝陛下的信任
Of his holiness, and of the emperor.
为虔诚的英格兰人民所爱戴
And truly of all the faithful people of england.
如果我在行刺中遭遇不测怎么办
and if I should die in the attempt?
皇帝陛下会负责照顾你的家人
then the emperor would look after your family here on earth.
而天堂大门将为你敞开
And you would be welcomed into heaven,
受到天使的热烈欢迎
By a fanfare of angels.
英侵法领地
English Occupied France.
我最亲爱的兄弟
my dearest brother.
我的兄弟 朋友
mon fr猫re. mon ami.
欢迎
bienvenue.
我们此行的目的是重修我们的友谊
We are here to renew our friendship.
以及两国的邦交
And that of our two nations.
来 我们为此庆祝一番
Come! let us celebrate!
为了健康
For health.
这是场令人愉快的盛宴
This is a wonderful feast, brother.
- 谢谢 - 但是… 她在哪
- merci - but… where is she?
安妮夫人在哪儿
Where is the lady anne?
她会来的
she will be here.
我很抱歉 我妻子和妹妹
I am sorry my wife and sister.
改变主意不想和她会面了
changed their minds about meeting her.
你还指望什么呢
But what do you expect?
女人善变 谁要是疯了才会相信她们
Souvent femme varie, bien fol qui s'y fie!
women are often variable. only mad men believe them!
准确无误
exactement.
我考虑过
I have it in mind, brother,
我们之间
That you and i.
应当商议建立联合十字军的事宜
Should make arrangements for a joint crusade.
- 仿效理查一世 - 完全正确
- like… richard coeur de lion! - Absolument.
上帝的战士
Warriors of god.
当然 如果我们重新征服圣地
And of course, no one will be happier than his holiness.
教皇陛下将会欣喜无比
If we should commit ourselves to reconquer the holy land.
但有一点
but still,
我们将联合领导这次作战 对吗
We would be joint leaders in this venture. yes?
当然
of course!
大人
your grace.
您重得陛下重用 我深表欣喜
I'm delighted to see you returned to his majesty's good graces.
邀请您和公爵夫人
It gives me much pleasure.
到加来（法国北部港市）与我们共进晚餐
To invite you and the duchess.
是我莫大的荣幸
To dine with us while we are in calais.
能拒绝你的邀请
Not as much pleasure as it gives me.
我不胜荣幸 勋爵
To refuse your invitation. my lord.
有传闻说
There are rumours.
大人秘密支持王后
That your grace secretly supports the queen,
反对国王的要事
And are against the king in this great matter.
然而 长久以来
And yet, for so long, you took immense pride.
你一直对阴谋和政治不闻不问
In being totally indifferent to the machinations and politics of this world.
你这是怎么了
So what happened to you?
今时不同往日
I grew up.
波林夫人 重返法国一定很兴奋吧
mistress boleyn! you must feel so excited to be back in france,
毕竟这里有你小小的冒险经历
After all your little adventures here.
别说了 马克
Tut, mark.
你该记得我还在为我那可怜的丈夫戴孝
You ought to remember that I'm still in mourning for my poor husband.
我不应该把他叫做可怜人 应该是乏味
well, i wouldn't have called him poor. dull, certainly.
- 而且还不举 - 真的吗
- And impotent. - Really?
我都等不及趁着这里
I can't wait to ride.
狂乘一些年轻的法国种马
Some young french stallion while I'm here.
私底下说
well, between you and me,
我也迫不及待了
Neither can i!
棒极了
Magnifique!
她很迷人
She's ravishing.
精彩
bravo!
你是谁
qui tes vous?
我认识你吗
Do I know you?
原来是美丽的安妮
La belle anne.
你们姐妹还在法国的时候
When you and your sister were here in France.
都期待成为我的王后
As ladies in wating to my Queen.
我记得很清楚
I remember it so well.
陛下仁慈宽厚
Your Majesty is very gracious,
或许您知道我的一些事
but there are some things, perhaps which your majesty knows about me.
我希望您保密 永不要向国王提起
which I would rather you kept secret, and never mention to the King.
侯爵夫人
Madame la marquise,
我可是法国人
I am a frenchman.
我不会泄露女性的秘密
I would never betray the secrets of a woman,
尤其拥有许多秘密的漂亮女士
Especially a beautiful woman, who must naturally have a great many.
你真的支持我和国王的婚姻吗
do you really support my marriage to the king?
当然 首先
bien 茅videmment. for one thing,
我讨厌那位君主
I hate the emperor,
任何让他痛苦的事
So that anything which discomforts him,
诸如他的姑姑离婚之事
Like the divorce of his aunt,
令我欢心鼓舞
Pleases me immeasurably.
但我知道你与法国是同一阵线
But also, i know you are a friend of france,
所以… 我们可以做交易
So… we can do business.
- 但还有别的什么？- 是的
- but there is something else? - oui.
我不应该说这话的 但是…
It is not my place to say this, madam, but…
我们都这么熟了
Perhaps we know each other well enough.
事实上 你要登上的宝座
The fact is, the station you will be asked to occupy.
并不那么轻松
Is not an easy one…
尤其是对那些并非注定享有宝座的人
Especially to those not born to it.
想坐拥一切更是举步维艰
It is much harder to have everything than to have nothing.
如果我不是生来就是国王
If I had not been born to be king,
我肯定不会希望背负那样的命运
I would certainly not have wished that fate upon myself.
你明白吗
Vous comprenez?
是的 我明白 陛下
oui, oui, je comprends.majest茅.
我已尽力逃离燃烧我激情的火焰
I've tried to run from the fire that burns me.
但当我四处找寻时
But when I look around,
火焰依旧燃烧
There the fire still is.
姐姐
sister.
还记得当时的状况
When you remember how it was,
我们原来在这的时候
When we were here before.
你有没有预见到现在的结果 玛莉
Could you ever have imagined this, mary?
无论如何都没想到
not for all the world.
我没有你聪明
But then I am not as clever as you.
我保证
I promise you.
我只告诉你一个人
and I can tell only you.
我梦寐以求的愿望
That the thing I have so longed for.
将在这里实现
Will be accomplished here.
我认为弗兰西斯的表现值得赞赏
I thought francis behaved himself rather admirably.
你可真美
You looked beautiful.
好了 亲爱的
now, my love…
让我怀孕
Let me conceive.
我们将会生下一个儿子
And we will have a son.